<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse on 2 Cor. III. 6 ... by Samuel Tomlyns ...</title>
            <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62906</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1858A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37158</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16262980</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16262980</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105152</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62906)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105152)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1602:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse on 2 Cor. III. 6 ... by Samuel Tomlyns ...</title>
                  <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Three p. of advertisement bound at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and tightly bound with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, III, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105152:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105152:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE On 2 Cor. III. 6. <hi>Who alſo hath made us Able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit: For the Letter kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, but the Spirit giveth Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>Samuel Comlyns,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Marleborough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> at the Lower End of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105152:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105152:2"/>
            <head>THE DEDICATION, To my Well-beloved Friends in Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Stephen Lock,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Smith,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Iſgar,</hi> and other Chriſtian Friends living in <hi>Goſpert,</hi> Grace, Mercy, and Peace be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply'd.</head>
            <p>IT is near Thirty years ago that I was firſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with ſome of you, and Converſant among you, Preaching the Goſpel of the Kingdom of God, I am now drawing towards the Confines of Time, and the Borders of Eternity: I was therefore willing to Dedicate this Diſcourſe of Chriſt's Teſtament to you, as a Grateful Acknowledgment of your Kindneſs to me, and as a Token and Pledge of that Real Love that I bare towards you. The Teſtament of Chriſt is the moſt Noble, and Sweet Subject that your Minds can be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant about, and your Affections feed on that which was contrived from Eternity, may well be Matter of Contemplation in time, and of Admiration to Eternity. This Teſtament was drawn in the Mind, and Counſel of God before the Foundations of the World, and hath been ſince Written in the Blood, and eſtabliſhed by the Death of the Son of God: In it there are the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and ineſtimable Legacies Bequeathed. God gives
<pb facs="tcp:105152:3"/>himſelf as a Father and Portion, Jeſus Chriſt gives himſelf as a Husband, and the Spirit is given as a San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifier and Comforter; and Chriſtians are cauſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Church, and Heaven, that once were deſolate Heritages, as to them, though the Teſtator be alive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, yet this doth not leſſen our Portion, or worſt our Eſtate, <hi>Iſa. 4.8.</hi> as the Death of Chriſt doth Purchaſe, ſo the Life of Chriſt is powerful to conveigh, and beſtow his Legacies. Chriſt hath paſſed through the moſt hard and difficult part of his Work, <hi>Rom. 5.10.</hi> he died to reconcile us, that he may live, and ſave us; and may ſit in Heaven and Enrich us, and perfect whatever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns our Happineſs. Conſider theſe following parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, in Relation to the Teſtament of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> The Wiſdom of God ſhines in this, that ſuch a way ſhould be found out to ſet God's Houſe in Order, and to diſpoſe of the moſt Rich, and Great Eſtate; all ways of Communicating Good to the Creature ſeemed to be ſhut up, and obſtructed by the Guilt of Sin. God's Treaſury was Locked, his Fountain Sealed, his giving Hand Bound: but Chriſt died for the Redemption of Tranſgreſſions, <hi>Heb. 9.15.</hi> to buy off thoſe ſins that would ſeparate between God and us, that would hinder good things from us, and ſink us down into the Bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit, and ſhut us up in the Eternal Priſon. The Conveyance therefore of a Rich Eſtate, to Guilty, Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly, Bankrupt Creatures, through the Death, and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament of Chriſt, is the bare contrivance of Infinite Wiſdom. In the Lord's Supper, the Seal of Chriſt's Teſtament, his Blood is ſet forth, as Purchaſing us to be a peculiar People, <hi>Acts 20.10.41.15.</hi> and his Fleſh is ſet forth as Bread, to ſtrengthen and enable us to perform our Duty towards our Saviour. By Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, we are obliged to be Firſt-Fruits to God and
<pb facs="tcp:105152:3"/>the Lamb, <hi>Rev. 14.4.</hi> and, by Regeneration, we are fitted to be Firſt-Fruits, <hi>James 1.18.</hi> that is, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate and devote our ſelves to God and Chriſt, and to live to them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Conſider the Admirable Righteouſneſs of God that appears in this Teſtament that Jeſus Chriſt purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, what he Bequeathed: he is a Prieſt of good things, <hi>Heb. 9.1.</hi> that is, he Merited, he procured them by his Death. Good things do not come to us, as a Gift from Chriſt Living, but as a Legacy from Chriſt Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It is now juſt with God to forgive the ſins of Believers, <hi>John 1.9.</hi> It might have been juſt with God to puniſh and deſtroy; but now, through the Death of Chriſt, it is juſt for God to Forgive. Grace may now Reign, through Righteouſneſs, to Eternal Life, <hi>Rom. 5. laſt.</hi> And they that receive an Abundance of Grace, and of the Gift of Righteouſneſs, ſhall Reign in Life, <hi>Rom. 5.17.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt doth not, as other Teſtators by Death, leave the Inheritance empty, but Purchaſes a Right for us, to enter upon the Inheritance, and to poſſeſs and enjoy it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Conſider the wonderful Grace of God, and Chriſt, that is manifeſted in this Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That Chriſt ſhould Conſtitute us as his Heires, then he might have Executed us as Malefactors.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That when the Threatnings were in force for our Death, that Jeſus ſhould die to put the Promiſes in force for our Life; that he ſhould ceaſe to live for a time, that we might live eternally.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That he ſhould make a Teſtament to enrich us with Spiritual and Eternal Bleſſings, when we had, by ſin, forfeited our Lives, and deſerved to be ſtript of all Temporal Comforts and Enjoyments.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105152:4"/>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> That Jeſus Chriſt ſhould become poor to enrich us, <hi>2 Cor. 8.9. He became poor, that we by his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty might be made Rich.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt had no Houſe to put his Head in, he lived on what others Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to him, <hi>Matth. 8.20. Luke 8.3.</hi> He was robbed of his good Name, and cenſured as a Blaſphemer of God, and Condemned as an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper, and Enemy to <hi>Caeſar;</hi> they ſtript him of his Garments, and did not ceaſe afflicting him, till every drop of Strength was gone out of his Body, and every ſpark of Life was quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and he became a weak cold Carcaſe. Chriſt was thus emptied to fill us, and ſtooped ſo low to lift us up to Glory.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> What the Law of God requires, as a Duty, by Chriſt it is Bequeathed as a Legacy, and beſtowed as a pure Gift: What is required of the Heirs of Promiſe is purchaſed for them, by the Blood of the Teſtator, and wrought in them by the Spirit of Promiſe. They are <hi>changed from Glory to Glory, as by the Spirit of the Lord, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>3.</hi> laſt. The Holy Ghoſt doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite, actuate, and draw forth Grace: This North and South Wind, blowing on Chriſt's Garden, doth cauſe the Spices of it flow forth, <hi>Cant. 4. laſt.</hi> If Duties were required to be performed by our Free-will, and Natural Strength, the New Covenant would not differ from the Covenant of Works. The Firſt Promiſe was a moſt Free and preventing Promiſe, and, in it, undertakes to break the League and Amity that was between the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and the Serpent, and to kindle Enmity between them and their Seed, <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi> And this Free Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was to be apprehended by Faith only: God doth not ſay, Do, and your Soules ſhall live; but hear, that is, Believe, and your Soules ſhall live, <hi>Iſa. 55.3.</hi> The Promiſe doth not run thus, I will be your God, if
<pb facs="tcp:105152:4"/>you will be my People: but, I will be their God, and they ſhall be my People, <hi>Joel 31.33.</hi> Chriſt takes it upon himſelf, to fetch back, and bring home ſtraying Sheep, and, to cauſe them (<hi>Iſa. 29.19.</hi> though deaf, and dead, <hi>John 5.25.</hi>) to hear his voice, <hi>John 10.16.</hi> We cannot ſincerely enter into Covenant with God, till God, in a great meaſure, hath executed his Covenant in us; whence Miracles of Grace is to be wrought on us, that Gifts of Grace might be received by us; Till we have new hearts and ſpirits given to us, we ſhall but flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God, and lie to him in all our ſeeming Service, <hi>Pſal. 79.36, 37. Hoſ. laſt.</hi> It is bad to lie to God in all our Confeſſions of Sin, and Petitions for Grace, and Mercy. We muſt not therefore ſtay in the Exacting Letter of the Law, but have Recourſe to the Living Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament of Chriſt. The Law ſaith, be Holy, <hi>Deut. 20.7.</hi> But it is Chriſt that Sanctifies, <hi>Heb. 2.11.</hi> and as an everlaſting Father, doth propagate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive a new Divine Nature to us, <hi>Iſa. 9.6. 2 Pet. 1.4.</hi> We are bid to Love God, but it is Chriſt that Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes the Heart, <hi>2 Col. 11.</hi> To Love God, he cuts off the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean and Filthy Foreskin of Sinful Self-love, and Baptizes with his Spirit as with Fire. <hi>Deut. 30.6.</hi> to inflame our hearts with Love towards, and zeal for God, <hi>Matth. 3.11.</hi> We are charged to acquaint our ſelves with God, <hi>Job 22.21.</hi> but the Promiſe muſt help us here. <hi>All</hi> Zions <hi>Children ſhall be Taught of God, and ſhall all know me, from the greateſt to the leaſt,</hi> Iſa. <hi>54.13. Jer. 31.39.</hi> He that hath heard, and learned of the Father, comes to Chriſt, <hi>John 6.44, 45.</hi> We are enjoyn'd to keep God's Precepts diligently, <hi>Pſal. 119.4.</hi> but God hath promiſed to Write his Laws in our hearts, <hi>Jer. 31.33.</hi> We ought to live to, and walk with God, yet it is by virtue of
<pb facs="tcp:105152:5"/>his Spirit put into us, and cauſing of us to walk in his Statutes, and to keep his Commandments, <hi>Ezek. 36.27.</hi> All the Earth is called on to Fear God, <hi>Pſal. 33.8.</hi> but, that we may do it, God muſt put his Fear into our hearts, <hi>Jer. 32.40.</hi> We ought to Repent, but it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be, except God doth take away the heart of Stone, and give a heart of Fleſh, <hi>Mark 1.15. Ezek. 36.26.</hi> Faith it ſelf is compriſed in, and given by Chriſt's Teſtament to know God and Chriſt, containes Faith in it, <hi>Jer. 31.34.17. John 3. By his Knowledge,</hi> that is, by Believing on him, <hi>Chriſt Juſtifies many,</hi> Iſa. <hi>53.</hi> Chap. <hi>11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Conſider the Excellent, and Glorious Power, that executes this Teſtament, <hi>2 Cor. 4.7. Epheſ. 1.19.</hi> God ſaith he will be our God, and we ſhall be his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Jer. 3.33.</hi> God cannot be our God, if Idols are not caſt out; if Enemies are not dethroned, if Rivals, and Competitors, are not put from their nearneſs to, and intimacy with the Heart; and this the mighty Power, the glorious arm of God only can effect: And we can never be Gods People, if our blindneſs be not cured, our enmity conquered, if our Minds be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, and our Wills inclined to chooſe God for our chief good and only portion: Chriſt knocks, and it is he that muſt open the door, <hi>Rev. 3.20. Acts 16.14.</hi> It is he that calls, <hi>Iſa, 55.5.</hi> And muſt enable us to Eccho to his call, to ſay we are the Lords, <hi>Iſa. 48.5.</hi> and that he is our God, <hi>Zech. 13. laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Conſider the conſolation that may be drawn from this Teſtament, that we are ſo ſafe, that there is no condemnation to us, <hi>Rom. 8.1.</hi> becauſe Gods ſword hath awaked againſt Chriſt, <hi>Zech. 13.7.</hi> Our debt was exacted of him, our Curſe was executed on him, and that ſpiritual things are made ſo ſure to us by Chriſts death that is paſt, and by his Teſtament that
<pb facs="tcp:105152:5"/>is confirmed and made irrevocable; that there can be no detracting from its free Promiſes, or adding barder and heavier terms to it, <hi>Gal. 3.15.</hi> There is no diſanull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or adding to it: God promiſes to pour Waters on him that is thirſty, and floods on the dry ground, <hi>Iſa. 44.3, 4.</hi> The Heavenly Husbandman will improve and inrich dry and barren ground. If the overflowing of <hi>Nilus</hi> makes <hi>Egypt</hi> fruitful, therefore we read of the Harveſt of the <hi>Kiezr, Iſa. 23.3.4.</hi> that Harveſt that is cauſed by the River; much more can the Spirit, as the River of God, make us fruitful.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> I would exhort you to make ſure your own concern, in an Intereſt in this Teſtament of Jeſus Chriſt; be is riſen from the dead to woo and eſpouſe Souls to himſelf, <hi>Rom. 7.4.</hi> If you be joined to the ſuerty of the Teſtament, and be Married to the Teſtator, all the Riches of this Teſtament ſhall be yours. God with Chriſt gives all things, <hi>Rom. 8.32.</hi> Eccho to Chriſts call, and open at his knock; let in the Heir of all things, and he will bring in his Righteouſneſs, his Riches, his fullneſs with him: Chriſt will come in and order our Thoughts, our Wills, Affections, and ſubdue all to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Iſa. 9.7. Pſal. 47.3.</hi> Chriſt will execute juſtice, and Judgment, <hi>Jer. 23.5.</hi> he will execute juſtice: He will do God right, in raiſing up fallen, bringing back ſtraying alienate ſinners to God, <hi>Iſa. 49.56.</hi> And he will execute judgment in deſtroying Satan, and his works, <hi>Heb. 2.15. 1 John 3.8.</hi> Though there were many Creatures in the Earth, yet <hi>Adam</hi> was counted to be alone till a VVoman was made for him to ſet his love on: So though you have abundance of Creature enjoyments, yet count your ſelves to be alone till you Know, Love and Marry Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Expreſs your gratitude, and thankfulneſs to God
<pb facs="tcp:105152:6"/>and Chriſt for this Teſtament, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Brethren we are debters,</hi> Rom. <hi>8.12.</hi> Never were any ſuch great debters, as believers are to God and Chriſt; you were Reconciled when Enemies, juſtified when <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, <hi>Rom. 5.2. Rom. 4.4.</hi> Righteouſneſs hath looked down from Heaven, <hi>Pſal. 55.11.</hi> And Bread hath been rained down from Heaven, when it ſhould have ſprung up and grown out of the Earth: How wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful is it that Enmity ſhould be ſlain, <hi>Iſa. 61.1. Iſa. 49.9. Iſa. 49.24. Epheſ. 2.16.</hi> and yet Enemies be ſpared and reconciled? That Sin ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, <hi>Rom. 8.3.</hi> yet Sinners be pardoned, <hi>Col. 2.13.</hi> That Chriſt came to deſtroy Satans work only, <hi>John 1.38.</hi> but to heal, revive and ſet at liberty thoſe that were the workmanſhip of God; he releaſes Priſoners, and delivers thoſe that were lawful Captives, <hi>Heb. 2.18. Rom. 8.2. They are turned from the power of Satan to God, and made free from the Law of ſin and death, Rom. 8.2.</hi> Children of wrath might have been made Veſſels of wrath; have been filled up with Gods fury, and have been daſhed to pieces by that Rod of Iron that is in Chriſts hand. In the Law, if a Husband was Arreſted for debt, his VVife and Children might be ſold to pay the debt, <hi>Matth. 15.25.</hi> and to free the Husband and Father: But what Grace is this, that Chriſt who is the Everlaſting Father and Husband of the Church, ſhould be ſold to pay our debts? As <hi>Eve</hi> was hid in <hi>Adam,</hi> and by a Divine Power, <hi>Iſa. 9.6. 2. Cor. 11.2.</hi> brought forth out of him, ſo the Church was hid in Chriſt, formed and drawn out of Chriſt, caſt into the deep ſleep of death, <hi>Ezek. 47.11. John 19.34.</hi> O rejoyce in Chriſts Teſtament, glory in his Riches, Triumph in his Salvation, that when ſin reigns over moſt unto death, grace ſhould reign over you thro' the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt unto Eternal life.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105152:6"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Cor. III. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Who alſo hath made us Able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit: For the Letter Killeth, but the Spirit giveth Life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the words, 1. we have a Subject ſpoken of, and that is the New Teſtament, as it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from the Old Teſtament, which was not the Covenant of Works, but the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, wrapt up in Types, and Figures, more darkly Adminiſtred, <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.18. 2. The Apoſtle inſiſts on this New Teſtament, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends it, that it is Spirit and not Letter, 1 <hi>John</hi> 17. that is, the Holy Ghoſt doth eminently, and ſignally manifeſt himſelf in this New Teſtament Diſpenſation. It is Filled, it is Enriched, it is En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted by the Holy Ghoſt; he doth ſo breath in it, and worketh it, that it may well be called Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and not Letter. The Goſpel is not a meer Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral Doctrine, or Command, but mightily anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Spirit; if it were only Letter, it would kill us frail and weak Greatures, exacting Duty, And requiring Obedience of us, that are Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, yea dead Creatures; but it is Spirit, and ſo it gives Life. The Holy Ghoſt enlightens Blind Minds, ſoftens Hard Hearts, and Quickens Dead Souls. The effectual Workings of the Spirit, are called, <hi>the Law of the Spirit,</hi> and this Law of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105152:7"/>Spirit of Life is ſaid to <hi>make free from the Law of ſin and death,</hi> Rom. 8.2. This is a Law that is all Power, and conſiſts wholly in Execution. 3. The Apoſtle informs us of the Honour and Dignity of Goſpel-Officers, for they are Miniſters of this New Teſtament. 4. The Apoſtle glorifies God, and inſtructs us, how it is that Officers do become able Miniſters of this New Teſtament. It is God that made <hi>Paul,</hi> and others, <hi>Able Miniſters of the New Teſtament:</hi> The words afford us Three Doctrines. 1ſt. That there is a New Teſtament. 2dly, That Goſpel Officers are Miniſters of this New Teſtament. 3dly, That it is God that doth make Men able Miniſters of the New Teſtament. 1. Doctrine, that there is a New Teſtament. We may obſerve and admire the Wiſdom of God, that firſt there was a Promiſe, then a Covenant, then a Teſtament; this laſt the beſt, and moſt Noble Edition of the Covenant of Grace; this is called the New Teſtament, to diſtinguiſh it from the Old Teſtament. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Old Teſtament was made with one Nation, in the day that the Lord took <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the hand, to lead them out of the Land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> but it is God's deſign, by Chriſt, and the New Teſtament, to gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into one all the Children of God that are ſcattered abroad, <hi>John</hi> 6.52. Chriſt Preacheth now not onely to the <hi>Jews</hi> that were nigh, but alſo to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that were afar off, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.17. 2. The Firſt Teſtament had <hi>Moſes</hi> for â Mediator, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19. <hi>The Law was given by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but Grace and Truth comes by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 John 17. Jeſus is the Madiator of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. The Old Teſtament was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105152:7"/>with Figures, and Shadows of things to come, 2 <hi>Col.</hi> 17. The Law had a ſhadow of good things to come, and not the very Image of the Things, that is, Chriſt himſelf; and the very Live Image of Spiritual things, were not then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited: Righteouſneſs was not yet brought, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement was not yet made, the <hi>Fountain</hi> was not yet <hi>opened for ſin and uncleanneſs: The Law and Prophets Propheſied till John,</hi> Matth. 1.13. they ſpake of Chriſt, and foretold the Glorious things of the Goſpel, as yet to come; but now the Kingdom of God is clearly diſcovered, and is Preached as come, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ourthly.</hi> The Old Teſtament, and the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Law made nothing perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.19. but did introduce the Hope of a better Prieſt, and of a more Noble Sacrifice; but Chriſt, by one Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hath perfected for ever them that are Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: On the day of Atonement there was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of all the Sins committed that year, which did ſhew the weakneſs and imperfection of thoſe Sacrifices, in that there was a Remembrance again made of Sins. But in this the Excellency and Perfection of Chriſt's Sacrifice appears, in that it did purge and put away Sin; and God on the account of it made that Promiſe, <hi>Your Sins and Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities I will Remember no more, Heb.</hi> 10.17, 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly.</hi> The Old Teſtament was confirmed by the Blood of Beaſts; <hi>Moſes killed Sacrifices and took the Blood of them, and ſprinkled it on the People; ſaying, behold the Blood of the Covenant that God hath made with you:</hi> But the New Teſtament was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with better Blood. Chriſts Blood is the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105152:8"/>Blood of Sprinkling, and the Blood of the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly.</hi> The Old Teſtament was weak and faulty; it did not, it could not purge Conſcience by the Blood of Brutiſh Sacrifices; neither could it introduce the Law of God into the Soul, and write it in the Heart; but the New Teſtament is ſtrong and powerful, it makes thoſe that were barren to bear and rejoyce, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.1. And by it the Law of God is writ in the Heart, and put into the inward parts, and the Soul is Renewed and Transformed, to walk with, and live to God.</p>
            <p n="7">7thly. The Old Teſtament waxed old, and did vaniſh away, but the New Teſtament remains, abides and is Everlaſting, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20. the Blood of Chriſt is ſtill freſh, and therefore his Teſtament is ſtill new. <hi>He offered one Sacrifice for Sins for ever, Heb.</hi> 10.12. His Sacrifice is of an Everlaſting Virtue, and the way made by it to the true Holy of Holies is living, and ſtill new, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19. and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and Teſtament built on this Everlaſting Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, muſt need be Everlaſting. This is God's laſt ſpeaking to the World, and it ſhall never give place to any other Covenant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.1. This is a better Covenant, or Teſtament, eſtabliſhed on better Promiſes, than the Covenant of Works was, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6. yea, the Promiſes of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are clearer, and exhibit more grace, than the Promiſes of the Old Teſtament. The Old Covenant is compared to, and ſet forth by <hi>Hagar,</hi> that was a young Woman, and had Natural Strength to conceive, and bare a Son, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24, 25. with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.1. but the New Teſtament is ſet forth by <hi>Sarah</hi> that was barren, and was made
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105152:8"/>fruitful by a ſupernatural power, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11. The Promiſes of the Law do reſpect the ſtrength that God firſt put into Man, and are built on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to be performed by this ſtrength; but the New Teſtament is built on a Spiritual and Supernatural ſtrength put into the Soul by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>For the opening, and Explication of this New Teſtament I ſhall inſiſt on theſe ſeveral particulars. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Who is the Teſtator? Anſwer, This muſt needs be he, that by his Death, doth confirm, and eſtabliſh the Teſtament, and this is proper to the Son of God, he is the only Mediator of the New Teſtament. He procured it, and gave force to it by his Sufferings and Death, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.29. Chriſt ſpeaks of himſelf as bequeathing, and acting as a Teſtator, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I bequeath, I diſpoſe unto you a Kingdom. <hi>Budaeus,</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentary on the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue, doth confeſs and acknowledge; that this is <hi>Verbum Teſtamentale,</hi> a word commonly uſed by the <hi>Grecians</hi> in making their Wills. The Father is ſaid to diſpoſe a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to the Son, the Son to us. <hi>The Father hath made Chriſt heir of all things,</hi> Heb. 1.2. <hi>He hath given him a Name above every Name, that at the Name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow.</hi> But in this God hath an eye, and a reſpect to the Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Sufferings, and Death of Chriſt, becauſe he became obedient to the Death of the Croſs; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hath exalted and glorified him. The Death of Chriſt ſeems to be the ground of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers legacy to Chriſt, and of all that Jeſus Chriſt bequeathes and diſpoſes to us.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105152:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In a Teſtament there muſt be an Eſtate to be diſpoſed of, and the Teſtator muſt have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, and be intereſted in this Eſtate. elſe he cannot diſpoſe it: Chriſt ſaith, <hi>All things that the Father hath are mine, John</hi> 16.15. Therefore Chriſt hath good right to diſpoſe of them. Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors do diſpoſe of two ſorts of things, Money and Goods, and Houſes and Lands; the Graces Chriſt beſtows may be compared to Money, and Goods: The Glory he bequeathes, is ſet forth by an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Houſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. and an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Inheritance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt bequeathes Grace, and a new Nature: <hi>A new Heart will I give unto you, a new Spirit will I put within you,</hi> Ezek. 36.26.31. <hi>I will put my Law into your inward parts, and write it in your hearts, Jer.</hi> 33. The Law is put deep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Soul, and it is written for Perpetuity, never to be blotted out, and it is diffuſed through the Soul; it ſpreads into the underſtanding, and it is rooted and prevails in the Will. The Soul is poor, blind, dead, and all its Faculties are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and diſorderly; without this new Heart, without the Law of God written in the Mind, and Will: How full, large and comprehenſive is Chriſts Teſtament? It doth not only make Heirs, but alſo raiſes up Children, which no other Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth or can do. True Believers are Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Promiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8. <hi>Iſaac</hi> was born of the free and powerful Promiſe of God: This was the word of Promiſe, <hi>At this time I will come and Sarah ſhall have a Son, Rom.</hi> 9.9. God would make an effectual viſit, he would put forth his Power in an excellent and extraordinary way,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105152:9"/>and ſo <hi>Sarah</hi> ſhould conceive (though barren) and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> tho' old be born. So God comes to Souls dead in ſins and Treſpaſſes, he beams in light, and breathes in life, and ſo they are Regenerated and born to God: The Covenant of Grace, the Teſtament of Chriſt is <hi>Sarah,</hi> a Mother, of which we are born; and as there are Children of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that derive Grace and a new Nature from the Promiſe, ſo there are Heirs of Promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17.19. That do inherit the Kingdom, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Glory, by virtue of the free Promiſe. God is ſaid to Promiſe the Kingdom, and to Promiſe Eternal Life, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. Here are the Riches and fulneſs of this Teſtament, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are Children of the Promiſe, and ſo partake of Grace, and are Heirs of the Promiſe, and ſo do inherit the Kingdom of Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi> Where there is a Teſtament there muſt be Legatees and Heirs; Jeſus Chriſt is the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of the New Teſtament, that thoſe that are called may receive the Promiſe of the Eternal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. The Civil Law gives this deſcription of an Heir, that he is <hi>vocatus ad heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem;</hi> one that is called to the Inheritance by the Teſtament of a dead Man, <hi>Vid pacium:</hi> If Chriſt had not died as a Teſtator, there would have been no Inheritance to be enjoyed, and there would have been no call to a Heavenly Houſe and Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How many are there in the World that were never called at all, and others are not effectually called; the <hi>Jews</hi> at this day, are like ſuch as the Civil Law calls <hi>Abdicati,</hi> ſuch as for Provocations given are diſinherited; the Gentile Heathen World are like ſuch as the Civil Law calls <hi>Praeteriti,</hi> ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105152:10"/>as are paſſed by, and ſlipt over, but ſuch may come in for a ſhare in the Fathers Goods, and lay claim to his Inheritance; the blind deſolate Heathen World ſhall be called, and converted, <hi>The deſolate Cities ſhall be inhabited,</hi> Iſa. 54.3. <hi>And the deſolate Heritages ſhall be inherited,</hi> Iſa. 49.8. For the clearer explication of things I ſhall ſhew, 1. Who are the Heirs. 2. What they are Heirs of. 3. How they became Heirs. 1. Who are Heirs? I Anſwer, The Sons, the Children of God; there are ſome that are prediſtinated to the Adoption of Children, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.5. Chriſt is to gather together into one, that is, into one Kingdom, City, Family, Body, the Children of God that are ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, <hi>John</hi> 11.52. Theſe Sons, theſe Children ſhall be Heirs, the Inheritance is limited and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained unto them; to ſit on the right and on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> left hand of Chriſt in his Kingdom is not his to give, but to whom it is prepared of his Father, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.21.23. That ſupplement, <hi>but it ſhall be given to them,</hi> ſhould be wholly left out, and the words be thus rendred, <hi>To ſit at my right hand and my left is not mine to give, but to thoſe for whom it is prepared of my Father.</hi> Chriſt would give places in his Kingdom, but he was limited by the decree of the Father; to give to thoſe he had prediſtinated to the Adoption of Children, and ſo had prepared the Inheritance and Kingdom for them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What are Chriſts People Heirs of? I Anſwer, 1. Of the Kingdom, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.5. 2. Of the World, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13. 1. They are Heirs of the Kingdom, they ſhall have a Manſion in God's Houſe, <hi>John</hi> 14.2, 3. They ſhall have a Lot and Inheritance in the Heavenly Kingdom, in <hi>Emmanuels</hi> Land and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105152:10"/>Country, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. laſt. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12. They ſhall ſit in the Throne with Chriſt, and Reign in Life for evermore, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17. 2. They are Heirs of the World. God gave <hi>Abraham</hi> the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> by Promiſe, and this was a pledge and earneſt of all Earthly Portions, and Poſſeſſions given to Believers by God's free grace, and bounty. Wicked Men may be Poſſeſſors of, and dwellers in the World, but it is Believers that are Heirs of the World, and have a Spiritual Right and Title to it. Godlineſs hath the Promiſe of the Life that now is, and of that which is to come, <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.4.8. <hi>He hath given meat to them that fear him: He will ever be mindful of his Covenant, Pſal.</hi> 111.5. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and his Righteouſneſs is our chief good, and true Happineſs; the main of Gods Covenant is wrapt up in this, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.33. yet Earthly and outward things are Promiſed as an advantage, theſe ſhall be added to God's Children to ſupply their wants. The Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had need of a Paſſage to <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Country that God had given them, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſent to <hi>Sihon</hi> to deſire a paſſage through his Country unto <hi>Canaan, Deut.</hi> 2.26, 27, 28, 30. but he refuſed to let <hi>Iſrael</hi> paſs through his Land, ſo God gave him up to <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be deſtroyed. Thus the People of God muſt have ſome Footing in, and Poſſeſſion of the World, as it is a paſſage to the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> that is their proper Country, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.15, 16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How do Chriſtians become Heirs? I anſwer, By being effectually called. None but ſuch ſhall partake of the Eternal Inheritance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. When Chriſt doth not only ſeek after ſtraying Souls, but doth apprehend them, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105152:11"/>ſaith he was apprehended of Chriſt. When the Lord of Glory doth not only knock but open the Heart, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14. When the call of God is accompanied with gifts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. The gifts and calling of God are without Repentance; when God ſo calls, that he gives an underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to know him, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20. and gives a Heart to love and fear him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39. When God beſtows a new Heart, and a new Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, then is the call effectual, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly.</hi> Where there is a Teſtament, there muſt be a Sanction, Confirmation and Eſtabliſhment of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. Where there is a Teſtament, there muſt of neceſſity be the death of the Teſtator, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.16.17. The Civil Law ſaith as long as a Man lives, <hi>voluntas eſt perambulatoria,</hi> it is mutable, and changeable, but the Death of a Teſtator fixes things, and gives force to his Will, confirms and eſtabliſhes all his Legacies: How ſweet are theſe words, where there is a Teſtament, there muſt be the Death of the Teſtator? The Law ſpeaks at another rate, where there is a Crime, the Criminal muſt be puniſhed: Where there is a Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the threatening muſt be put in force, the Curſe muſt be executed, the Tranſgreſſor muſt be cut off, but here is a New Teſtament eſtabliſhed by the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>This is my Blood of the New Teſtament, Matth.</hi> 26.28. This Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> did ſpeak of God's making a New Covenant, or Teſtament, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31. but there is no mention made, or diſcovery given of the Blood, that this New Covenant was to be confirmed by; but the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105152:11"/>Goſpel teacheth us what the Blood is, by which the New Teſtament is eſtabliſhed: God did put the threatenings, and Curſe of the Law in force by cutting off Chriſt, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.8. That he might put the Promiſes in force, fulfill them to us, and beſtow the Eternal Inheritance on us. Who could have imagined, or thought of ſuch a thing, that the death of Sinners ſhould be prevented, and the death of a Teſtator ſhould ſucceed, and be in the place of their Sufferings and death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly.</hi> Where there is a Teſtament, there muſt be an effectual way to execute it. We read of the <hi>ſure Mercies of David,</hi> that is of Chriſt, as the next Verſe doth plainly evidence, that it is Chriſt that is ſpoken of, for he is ſaid to be given as a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as a Leader, and Commander to the People, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3, 4. This is obſervable, that all the Riches, Bleſſings, and Benefits of the Covenant are Chriſt's Mercies: He is a Prieſt of good things, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.11. he purchaſes, he procures them; and it is he alſo that diſtributes, and gives them out. In <hi>Iſaiah</hi> there is only mention made of the <hi>ſure Mereies of David,</hi> but in the <hi>Acts, Acts</hi> 13.34. it is thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed; <hi>I will give you the ſure Mercies of David:</hi> and this Promiſe is grounded on the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, who is now no more to return to Corruption, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.33, 34. As Chriſt died as a Teſtator, ſo he roſe again to be the Executor of his own Teſtament; he is not alive to Violate, or Diſanul, but to fulfil his Teſtament. So we are ſaid to be ſaved by his Life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. Jeſus Chriſt diſcharges all his Offices, by executing of his Teſtament.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105152:12"/>
            <p n="1">1. Jeſus Chriſt executes his Prophetical Office, <hi>No Man hath ſeen God, but the only begotten that is in the Boſom of the Father hath declared him to us,</hi> 1 John 18. Luke 1.7, 8. Iſa. 9.6. Mal. 3. laſt. He is the <hi>Day ſpring from on high,</hi> the <hi>Wonderful Counſellor,</hi> the <hi>Meſſenger of the Covenant;</hi> he Preached Righteouſneſs, and declared God's Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and Salvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.9, 10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Jeſus Chriſt executes his Prieſtly Office, in Sprinkling his Blood, as clean Water, to Purifie from Uncleanneſs, and to Waſh Men from their Sins, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.28. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5, 6. And Jeſus, as Prieſt, Intercedes that his Legacies may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd; and his Blood cries for the Execution of his Teſtament, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>He ever lives to make Interceſſion. John</hi> 17.19.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Jeſus Chriſt, as King, executes his Office, he writes his Doctrine and Laws in the hearts of his Subjects, and gives them new hearts, Jer. 31.33. <hi>Ezra</hi> 36.56.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> This may inform us of the wonderful Grace of God, that there ſhould be a New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Did Fallen Man ever imagine, or conceive ſuch a thing, that Chriſt's Goods ſhould be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed, and his Inheritance be derived to, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on Sinful Creatures by a Teſtament Ratified by his own Blood, and Death. 1. We deſerved to be ſtript, and deprived of all External and Temporal Enjoyments, that the Wine-preſs, and the Corn-floor ſhould not feed us, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9.2. That God ſhould return, and take away his Corn, Wool, and Flax from us, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.9. and that the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105152:12"/>things that God hath given us, ſhall paſs away from us, Jer. 8.13. God might, by the Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Threatnings, have impoveriſhed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd us; and what Grace is this, that he ſhould make a Teſtament to ſave, and inrich us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Covenant of Works doth exact perfect and perpetual Obedience: it requires the full Debt, without any abatement, of us poor Inſolvent Creatures, and threatens us with Eternal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Perdition, for any defect, failure, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault in our Obedience? And what Grace is this, that a New Teſtament ſhould be made, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gives the Guilty, and gives to the Poor? <hi>The Law was given by Moſes; but Grace and Truth came by</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 1.17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider how dear it coſt Jeſus Chriſt to be a Teſtator. 1. He was obliged to put on our Humane Nature, that he might have a Body to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up, a Life to lay down, Blood to ſhed, a Soul to pour out to the Death. 2. Jeſus Chriſt muſt be a Surety, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22. or elſe he could not have been a Teſtator: he muſt bear our ſins, pay our Debt, diſcharge our Ranſom; he muſt buy and purchaſe all good things for us, elſe he could not bequeath them to us. We were ſuch Criminals, ſuch guilty Creatures, that Jeſus Chriſt could not live, and give any good to us, or beſtow any Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Bleſſing on us, but he muſt die to bequeath Legacies; all Spiritual Good Things muſt come ſwiming to us in the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt. 3. That Jeſus Chriſt ſhould empty himſelf to fill us, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſh himſelf to inrich us. You know (ſaith
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105152:13"/>
               <hi>Paul) The grace of our Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>that though he was rich, yet, for our ſakes, he became poor, that we, through his Poverty, might be Rich,</hi> 2 Cor. 8, 9. The Lord of Heaven and Earth, the Heir of all things, was in a meaner and lower condition than Birds and Foxes. <hi>The Birds of the Air have Neſts, and Foxes have Holes, but the Son of Man hath not where to lay his Head,</hi> Luke 9.58. The Curſe took hold of him, that the Bleſſing might flow to us. Death came to him, that Life might be derived to us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider how ſweet, comfortable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing Chriſt's Teſtament is.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In a Covenant there are Two Parties obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging themſelves to each other; but, in a Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there is but one Party Bequeathing, and that is Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Covenants are Vacated, and Diſanulled by the Death of one, or both of the Confederates, but a Teſtament is not diſanulled, but eſtabliſhed by the Death of Chriſt. We are Heires, in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and Heires, in Poſſeſſion, by our own Death.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Teſtament is irrevocable, becauſe it is built on ſomething paſt, and that cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done: Jeſus Chriſt hath died, and this gives e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal force to his Teſtament. The Benefits, and Legacies of Chriſt's Teſtament come to us in a Righteous way, what he Bequeathes he Purchaſes, and there is a powerful and effectual way to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Chriſt's Teſtament. The Holy Ghoſt fulfills the Promiſes, and beſtowes the Legacies of this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105152:13"/>Teſtament. Men are Taught, and do know God as the true God, and their God; they are drawn, and do chooſe God for their God, and Portion, and do ſincerely become a Peculiar People to him, and they are cauſed to walk in his Statutes, and to keep his Judgments and Commands.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Exhortation,</hi> 1. <hi>Branch.</hi> O ſeek to have Benefit by Chriſt's Teſtament, to be his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatees, yea his Heires! O be not contented with a ſhort Reprieve, and with meer Patience and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance; Do not ſatisfie your ſelves with ſome preſent Almes of Mercy, and Temporary Relief, but ſeek a Rich, and laſting Portion, an Eternal Inheritance: Let not this quiet you, that you are Stewards of Temporal Things, but make ſure you ſhall be Heires of an everlaſting Salvation and Kingdom. Do not onely catch at God's Riches, in Earthly things, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.24.3. but lay hold of the Riches of Chriſt for Eternity, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 8. O prize and ſecure your Intereſt in this Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for, 1. It mainly and principally reſpects the Soul, and Eternity: The Soul ſhall find reſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.2. of it ſelf, in fatneſs, and obtain Salvation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. 2. This is a Comprehenſive Teſtament, here is Grace given, and Glory bequeathed, 1. <hi>Galat.</hi> 6. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here are the greateſt, moſt precious, and Invaluable Legacies beſtowed; God gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as our God, Father, and Portion, Jer. 31.33. and Jeſus Chriſt beſtowes himſelf, as a Head, Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and Saviour, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.23.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:105152:14"/>
            <p>That you may have benefit by this New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I would Counſel and Adviſe theſe Two things, 1. O be Married to Jeſus Chriſt the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtator, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. as <hi>Adam</hi> awaked out of his deep ſleep to Marry <hi>Eve,</hi> ſo Chriſt is awaked, and Riſen from the Dead to Marry poor Soules, and to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle his Riches, and Inheritance on them. 2. Cry, and ſeek for the Spirit, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.2.13. he is the Faithful, and Powerful Executor of Chriſt's Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament; he can open blind Eyes, break hard Hearts, quicken dead Soules.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. <hi>Branch of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Exhortation.</hi> O be Grateful, be Thankful to the Teſtator, that hath eſtabliſhed this New Teſtament; give your ſelves to Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. and ſerve him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.30. Yield your ſelves to God, as thoſe that are alive from the dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. Offer your ſelves to God as living Sacrifices, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. Turn to Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.21. Run to Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.15. Live to him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15.54. Be his Portion, and Poſſeſſion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8. Be Firſt-Fruits to God, and the Lamb, as thoſe that are obliged to it by Redemption, and as thoſe that are enabled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by Regeneration. We are Redeemed to be Firſt-Fruits, we are Begotten to be Firſt-Fruits, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4. <hi>James</hi> 1.18.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. <hi>Doctrine.</hi> Goſpel Officers are Miniſters of the New Teſtament; this is their Honour, and Glory, that they are ſent forth into the World with the Word, and glad Tidings of Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in their Mouths, and the Teſtament of the Son of God in their Hands. 1. They are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105152:14"/>to the World this Great Secret, this deep, and wonderful Myſtery, that the Son of God hath ſet his Houſe in Order, and made his laſt Will and Teſtament. The World is an utter ſtranger to this Supernatural Truth, the Church only knows it, and is acquainted with it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.14. This is ſpoken of as a great Mercy, that God will Reveal this Secret, and ſhew his Covenant unto any. 2. Chriſt's Officers are to open, explain, and expound this Teſtament; it is ſo Rich, Full, and Comprehenſive, that Miniſters may Study. Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, Contemplate on it all their days, and Preach it throughout their whole Life. This is the Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and Noble Employment of Miniſters to Preach to the World the unſearchable Riches of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. They are to give forth the Savour of Chriſt's Ointments, to pour out his Name as Ointment; to ſhed abroad the ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Knowledge of God, and Chriſt, in every place; to bear Chriſt's Name before the World, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.15. The Church is compared to a Company of Horſes in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Chariot; as by her Officers ſhe draws Chriſt's Spiritual Chariot, and him ſitting in it through the World, 1 <hi>Cant.</hi> 9. with 3 <hi>Cant.</hi> 9, 10. 3. They are to urge, and preſs on Men to lay hold of this Covenant, of this Teſtament of the Son of Cod: As it is eminent Grace in God to ſhew us this Covenant, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.14. ſo it is our main, and moſt important duty to lay hold on this Covenant, on this Teſtament, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.4.6. We have nothing to relieve our Fainting and Famiſhing Soules, we have nothing to bear up our ſinking Spirits, but the Teſtament of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:105152:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. Here is a moſt clear Revelation of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Eternal things, Life and Immortality is brought to light by the Goſpel, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. The way to the Holieſt of all, was not yet made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, while as the firſt Tabernacle was yet ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Vaile ſtood, and continued before the moſt Holy Place, notwithſtanding all the Sacrifices of the Law: but, when Chriſt died, the Vaile of the Temple was rent from the top to the bottom, and we have boldneſs to enter into the Holieſt, even into Heaven it ſelf, by the Blood of Chriſt. The inviſible World is more diſcovered.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Covenant and Teſtament is ordered in all things, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. it is ſo wiſely ordered, as that it meets with all our Objections, and may ſilence them: It meets with our doubts and fears, and may baniſh them: It meets with all our wants, and ſupplies them. It is ſo ordered that there is a Legacy ſuited to all the Noble, and Principal faculties of our Souls. 1. God Promiſes concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Elect People, that they ſhall all know him from the greateſt to the leaſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.34. Here is a Legacy of Light, and Knowledg to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. 2. God promiſes Pardon, that he will be merciful to Unrighteouſneſs, and will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Sins and Iniquities no more, in the ſame Text. Here is a Legacy to the Conſcience: It is Pardon that doth quite Conſcience, and eſtabliſh its peace.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is a further Legacy, that God will write his Law in the Heart, and put it into the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105152:15"/>inward parts; this is a pretious and noble Legacy to the Will, to renew, byaſs and rectify it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Teſtament hath the ſtrongeſt confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: Of old God gave his Oath to ſhew the immutability of his Counſel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17, 19. That the Heirs of Promiſe might have ſtrong Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but now the Son of God hath bled, and his Teſtament is eſtabliſhed by his own death, <hi>Heb.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.15.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What can we look for, if we are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in this Teſtament? A day of Wrath, Vengeance and Deſtruction will be our portion. We ſhall be ſtript, and deprived of all Good, and be loaded and burthened with all Evil: We ſhall be felled down as barren Trees for the Fire, be vinnowed as chaff out of the Floor into the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, and be ſilled up as Veſſels of Wrath.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Of Information: This ſhews us how Excellent, and Honourable the Office of Chriſts Miniſters is, that they are imployed, and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant about the Teſtament of the Son of God; that they are to open its Fulneſs, Explain and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover its Riches, and to urge and preſs Men to lay hold of it. They are to warn Men of their danger out of Chriſt, and to preſs Men to fly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the City of Refuge, and ſit down under the ſhadow of Chriſt, and ſo to flee from the wrath to come. They are to beſeech Men through the Mediator, to be Reconciled to God, and to woo Men to be Eſpouſed to Chriſt, 2 <hi>Col.</hi> 13. They are to ſet forth the free Grace of God in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105152:16"/>giving all Treſpaſſes, and in giving liberally and largely, according to his Divine Power he gives all things, that appertain to Life and Godlineſs, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. And freely with Chriſt gives all things alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> If Goſpel-officers are Miniſters of the New Teſtament, this may Reprove ſuch as call themſelves, and would be accounted Miniſters of the New Teſtament, yet only Preach and preſs Moral Duties, and build up a Natural Religion, but ſeldom, or very little, touch on the great Principles, and Truths of the Goſpel, as if there were no Teſtator, or New Teſtament: They urge Duty, but they little themſelves under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and therefore are very unable to Reveal to others, How Men ſhall recover Life, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, attain Power and Strength, and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Eternal Inheritance? They Treat of the New Covenant, as if it were only a Miſtreſs to command Work, and not as a Mother to give Life and Strength: As if Chriſt was little more than a Political Head to make Laws, and exact Obedience to them, and not a Natural Head to give Life, and influences to his Members to enabl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them to obey.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Are Chriſts Officers Miniſters of the New Teſtament? Then, 1. This ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Miniſters to Preach, and People alſo to Hear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This ſhould encourage Miniſters to Preach; the Goſpel cannot be wholly Preached in vain:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105152:16"/>Jeſus Chriſt muſt have Sons to bear up his Name, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.17. and Heirs to poſſeſs his Goods, and Inheritance: He that ſowed in Tears, muſt reap in Joy, he muſt ſee his ſeed, and the Travel of his Soul, and be ſatisfied. God's Promiſes to Chriſt muſt be fulfilled, and executed, that he ſhall have the Heathen for his Inheritance, the utmoſt parts of the Earth for his Poſſeſſion. God's great Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant muſt receive a great and glorious Reward for his Work: All King's muſt fall down before him, as Worſhippers, all Nations muſt ſerve him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.10, 11. When Miniſters Preach the Goſpel, the Hand of the Lord is with them, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.21. to open hearts, to break the Rock in pieces, to draw Men to Chriſt, to ſubdue them to his Kingdom, and Government. As Chriſt ſpeaks in, ſo he works with his Miniſters when they Preach, Chriſt ingrafts the Word, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. with <hi>Mark</hi> 16. laſt. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21. And when they Teach, the Spirit writes an Epiſtle, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully impreſſes the Doctrine of the Goſpel on Mens Souls, the Wilderneſs muſt be manured, and Sowed: The Meal of Men muſt be Levened, Chriſt will come forth as a deliverer and turn. Men from Ungodlineſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.26. He will Circumciſe the Heart to love him, and Baptize with the Spirit, make Men free from the Law of Sin and Death, 2 <hi>Col.</hi> 11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3. and render them a willing People in the day of his Power, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. He will beget a Holy ſeed as an Everlaſting Father, and quicken Souls dead in Sins, and Treſpaſſes, as he is the Reſurrection and the Life.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:105152:17"/>
            <p n="2">2. This ſhould perſwade, and incourage Men to hear, and liſten to the Miniſters of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: It is very neceſſary, that Men ſhould b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſcned, and delivered from the Covenant o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Works, from a killing Letter, and a Miniſtry o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Condemnation. O liſten to the Miniſters of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> New Teſtament, lay hold of it; do not mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> light of all that Chriſt hath purchaſed and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>queathed: Do not continue Spiritually poor, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be ſhut out of the Kingdom, and come ſhort of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Glory of God. Do not ſatisfy your ſelves wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> momentary Enjoyments till you are driven out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this Earth, and turned into Hell. Attend on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſpenſation of the Goſpel, it is clothed and an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mated with the Spirit; this is a Seed ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that is changes the Soul: It is a writing tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alters the Table, and turns a Heart of Stone in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a Heart of Fleſh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. The Goſpel is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Glaſs that changes the Spectators, and transform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them into the glorious Image of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> laſt. The Holy Ghoſt is as a Tongue of fire o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, ſo that they do not ſpeak cold words, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they throw Coals into the boſomes of Sinners, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> caſt chaines of light and love about Souls, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.14. They ſow, but God makes t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Seed to take root and grow, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 7. Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters do call Sinners to come out of their Priſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but Chriſt opens the door, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14. They b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sinners to riſe and come out of their Graves, <hi>Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 5.1. but it is Chriſt that breathes Life into the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Though Chriſts Miniſters are many times poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet they make many Rich, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are Deacons of Chriſts Teſtament: They a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hands by which Jeſus Chriſt gives forth his Almes
<pb facs="tcp:105152:17"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:105152:18"/>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:105152:18"/>and diſtributes Spiritual Gifts. O come and hear the Goſpel, this may be the day of your Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A new Leaven may be laid in your Meal, and a new Byaſs may be put on your Wills, for over to incline your Hearts towards God: That word may be ingrafted, that may better and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble your ſtock, and enable it to bring forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruit to God. The Lord Jeſus may ſpeak that with a ſtrong hand to thy Soul, that Man ſpeaks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with a weak hand to thy Ear. God ſaith to <hi>Hoſes</hi> that he would ſtand on the Rock, and he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ould ſmite it, and it ſhould give forth Water, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>od.</hi> 17.6. If God had not been there <hi>Moſes</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould rather have ſtruck Fire out of the Rock, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>an have drawn out Water from it: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God ſtood on the Rock it did cleave, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eld Water abundantly when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſmote it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this my incourage Miniſters to ſmite the Rocky <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>arts of men with the Rod of the Word; that God, that Chriſt will be there to cleave the Rock, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to turn the Flint into a Fountain of Water, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 114. laſt. God's hand goes along with his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſign, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.22. When Chriſt Curcified is reached, then God lifts up a ſtandard and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlays an Enſign; and this cannot be in vain, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen God ſo lifts up his hand to the Gentiles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they preſently bring Zions Sons in their arms, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd carry her daughters on their ſhoulders, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey may be joined with, and to the Church. Chriſt by the Goſpel opens blind Eyes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.7. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal.</hi> 110.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.3. And by this Rod of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is ſtrength he ſubdues diſobedient, and Rebellious ſouls: While Miniſters do open the Riches of Chriſts Teſtament, he opens the underſtanding of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105152:19"/>Men to perceive, and diſcern, the Fulneſs, and Glory of this Teſtament, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.45. Chriſt takes away the vail from the Heart, unſtops the deaf Ear, and takes away the Heart of ſtone. Though Miniſters may ſeem but poor contempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, yet they bring Treaſure in Earthen Veſſels, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. There is a hidden Treaſure, and a Pearl of price to be found in the diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel. Chriſt executes his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and diſpenſes the Treaſures of his Grace, by the Preaching of the word of Life, and of the Goſpel of Salvation: The Goſpel is the Arm of the Lord, and the Miniſtration of the Spirit, and of Power, ſo that the dead ſhall hear the voice of the Son of God, and the deaf ſhall hearken to the word of Life, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.1. <hi>John</hi> 5.25. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.18.</p>
            <p n="3">3d. <hi>Doctrine.</hi> It is God that makes Men able Miniſters of the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. God the Father fits Men to be Laborers, and thruſts them forth notwithſtanding all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and diſcouragements into his Harveſt: It is not every one that is fit to pluck ſecure Sinners out of the fire, and compel them to come unto the Feaſt, <hi>Judes Epiſtle</hi> 23. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23. It is God the Father that muſt qualify for this noble and hard work.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. The Son of God makes able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12. He gave Gifts to Men, Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtors and Teachers: Chriſt gave them from
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105152:19"/>Heaven, when he aſcended up on high, and poured down the Spirit from on high, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.18. with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.15. By the Holy Ghoſt he furniſhed them with Light, Life, Zeal for the diſcharge of their Office.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. The Holy Ghoſt gives the inward call, and fits Men with Gifts and Graces for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of their Miniſtry: The Holy Ghoſt is ſaid to make overſeers of the Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 20, 28.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Queſtion.</hi> Wherein doth this ability to be Miniſters of the New Teſtament conſiſt? What is requiſite furniture to make Men able Miniſters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 1. They muſt have the word of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and of Wiſdom, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8. The word of Knowledge is a skill to open, explain and vindicate the great Principles of the Goſpel, the very Foundations of our Holy Religion. And the word of Wiſdom ſeems to ſignify an ability, and dexterity to apply the word ſutable to the various Conditions, and Exigences of Souls; to divide and apply it aright, that every Hearer may have his proper portion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ability conſiſts much in Spiritual Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the Power of the Word on their own Souls, and Conſciences. When Miniſters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves taſte that the Lord is gracious to them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. that he hath Reconciled them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18. when they have been caſt down, and raiſed up: When they have been wounded and healed: When they have taſted the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105152:20"/>of Sin, and the ſweetneſs of the Grace of Chriſt. <hi>Paul,</hi> when Chriſt called him from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, was three days blind, and did neither Eat or Drink; during this time <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to be under great anguiſh and anxiety of mind, for his former Enmity to Chriſt, and Perſecuting of his Church; at this time <hi>Saul</hi> did know the Terror of the Lord, how Terrible God would be to him if he did not faithfully Preach the Goſpel, and how Terrible the Lord would be to others, if they did not liſten to it, Embrace and Receive it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This ability conſiſts in love to Chriſt; the Love of Chriſt conſtrains us becauſe we thus judge, that if one dyed for all, then were all dead: The Apoſtle had a Spiritual mind, and did rightly judge of things, that if Chriſt died for us all, then we were all Spiritually dead, elſe we needed not that Chriſt ſhould die for us; yea, if Chriſt died for us all, then this was as effectual for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and deliverance, as if we had all died, yea, we all died in him, and with him. O how ſhould this heighten affection to, and inflame Love towards Chriſt. How ſhould Miniſters beſtir themſelves to gain Souls to Chriſt, that hath ſo much obliged them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This ability conſiſts much in tender com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions, and pitty to periſhing Souls. Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakens the pitty of his Diſciples when he bids them to go to the loſt Sheep of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael, Matth.</hi> 10.6. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith, if the <hi>Jews</hi> would not hear him, <hi>his Soul ſhould weep in ſecret places, his Eyes ſhould run down with Tears,</hi> Jer. 13.17.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105152:20"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſerved God with many Tears, and ceaſed not night and day to warn the <hi>Epheſians</hi> with Tears, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.19, 31. He tells the <hi>Philippians</hi> with with Tears, that there were ſome among them, <hi>that were Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3.18. And he wrote a Letter to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> with many Tears, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This ability conſiſts in great Self-denial, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15. <hi>I will very gladly ſpend and be ſpent for you, though the more abundantly I love you, the leſs I be loved: I (if I am offered on the ſervice, and Sacrifice of your Faith I therein rejoyce,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> If my blood be poured out as a Drink-offering to promote the Service, and Sacrifice of your Faith,) do therein Rejoyce. There is a great deal of difference between Lamps and Stars; Lamps muſt have Oil to feed them, elſe they will go out; but faithful Miniſters are compared to Stars, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. Theſe will ſhine, though they have no ſupplies, or contributions from below. The World is very ungrateful to Chriſts labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Servants, and afford them but a ſlender, and ſtarving Maintenance, yet they do not ceaſe to Preach, and ſhine to the World.</p>
            <p n="6">6. This ability conſiſts in their being certain, and fully aſſured of the Doctrine they Preach: <hi>They have known ſurely, that I came out from thee, and they have believed that thou didſt ſend me. We believe, and are ſure, that thou art that Chriſt the Son of the Living God,</hi> John 6.68, 69. <hi>Our Goſpel</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>came to you in much aſſurance, as ye know what manner of Men we were among you for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105152:21"/>your ſake. Paul</hi> did evidence by his fervent Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and his importunate pleading with them, that he was fully aſſured of the Truth, Excellency and Importance of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The ability of Miniſters conſiſts in their boldneſs and courage to ſuffer, and Patience in ſufferings, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>after we had ſuffered before, and were ſhamefully entreated at Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippi, we were bold in our God to ſpeak unto you the Goſpel of God with much contention.</hi> The Rulers and Elders of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſaw the boldneſs of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John;</hi> was not this high courage, and ſtrong boldneſs that the Apoſtles ſhould divide the World, and take every own his ſhare of it, to manure for God, to conquer for Chriſt, to build a Houſe, and Temple of God upon, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13, 4.15. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of this meaſure, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the meaſure of the Rule, that God had divided unto us; and that he did not ſtretch himſelf beyond his meaſure, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.14. and that he did not boaſt of things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out or beyond his meaſure: This was ſtrange boldneſs, to divide the World, and to ſeize and take every one his Lot and ſhare to ſubdue the Nations to God. And the Patience of the Apoſtles was invincible, in all their Tribulations they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced that they were counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his name ſake, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.41. <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced if he was offered on the Service and Sacrifice of the <hi>Philippians</hi> Faith, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.17. Bonds and Afflictions did not move <hi>Paul,</hi> neither did he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count his life dear unto himſelf, that he might finiſh his courſe with Joy, and the Miniſtry that he
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105152:21"/>had received of the Lord Jeſus to teſtify the Goſpel of the Grace of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.24. <hi>I am ready not only to be bound, but alſo to die at Jeruſalem, for the Name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> Acts 21.13. <hi>Paul</hi> and others did glory in Tribulations.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Miniſters</hi> are able when they take care of themſelves and of their own Souls. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the Elders of <hi>Epheſus, take heed to your ſelves, and to the Flock of God, over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you overſeers,</hi> Acts 20.28.</p>
            <p>Goſpel-officers are ſaid not only to have eyes before, that is, to look to God, and behind to look after the Flock committed to them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.6. but they are alſo ſaid to have eyes within, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.8. to look to themſelves, and to watch over their own Souls. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo circumſpect, and exact that he could call God to Witneſs as to his private actions, and the principles of them, and he could call men to Witneſs as to his publick Actions and Converſation. <hi>God is witneſs, and ye alſo, how Holily, juſtly and unblameably we behaved our ſelves among you that believe,</hi> 1 Theſ. 2.10.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſhould be diligent, and laborious. <hi>Being affectionately deſirous of you, we were willing to have imparted to you, not the Goſpel of God onely, but alſo our own Souls, becauſe ye were dear to us, as you know; how we exhorted, and comforted, and charged every one of you (as a Father doth his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,)</hi> 1 Theſ. 2.8. <hi>I kept back nothing that was profitable to you, but have ſhewed you, and have taught you publickly from houſe to houſe by the ſpace of three
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105152:22"/>years I ceaſed not to warn every one night, and day with Tears,</hi> Acts 20.20.31. 2 Tim. 4.2. Luk. 14.23. They ſhould be inſtant, and preſſing on Souls in Seaſon, and out of Seaſon, and compel gueſts to come into Chriſt feaſt. They ſhould labour to bring Sacrifices to the Spiritual Temple, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.20. And to preſent a beautiful Bride to the Son of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. 1 <hi>Col.</hi> laſt.</p>
            <p n="10">10. A door of Utterance is requiſite to make an Able Miniſter of the New Teſtament. <hi>Paul</hi> deſires the Prayers of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> that Utterance might be given to him, that he might open his Mouth boldly, to make known the Myſtery of the Goſpel: Again, he begs Prayers of the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> that God would open to him a door of Utterance: To ſpeak the Myſtery of Chriſt, Miniſters muſt not only be large Ciſterns, to hold a great deal of the Spiritual Waters of the Sanctuary; but alſo be fit Pipes to conveigh the Spiritual Waters unto others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Exhortation.</hi> If God makes men able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the New Teſtament, we ſhould lift up our Eyes, and Soules to God, and earneſtly beg him to fulfil his Promiſe to us, that he will give Paſtors according to his own heart, to feed his Flock with knowledge and underſtanding, Jer. 3.15. Sue to Chriſt to give Gifts from Heaven, ſuch as become a Glorified Saviour to beſtow, even Officers filled with the Gifts, and Graces of the Holy Ghoſt. Seek for ſuch <hi>Miniſters</hi> as <hi>Apollos</hi> was.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:105152:22"/>
            <p n="1">1. He was Inſtructed in the way of the Lord, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.25. He was not Rude, Ignorant, or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull in the VVord of Righteouſneſs; but was well Taught the way in which God comes to us, and the way by which we are to come to God, and enjoy Communion with him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He was Fervent in Spirit. It is this Holy fire, that muſt burn, and ſhed abroad the ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Knowledge of God. And this is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, that Chriſt's <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſhould overcome, and Triumph, by ſpreading abroad the Sweet Savour of the Knowledge of God, that they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer by a Perfume.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Apollos</hi> Taught diligently the Doctrine of Chriſt; he pleaded for God, and wooed for Chriſt; he was not ſlothful, and negligent. How earneſt is the Sun in running of its Race? How ſwift are the Stars in their daily motions, to give Light to the VVorld, even ſo ſhould <hi>Miniſters</hi> be. The promoting of the Kingdom of God is much carried on by a skilful, able, and powerful <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi> that is not only Light, but alſo Fire, ſuch as will be, not only Shining, but Burning Lights, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. God muſt ſhine into their hearts, to enable them to give forth the Light of the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Glory of God to others, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. this will make <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſhining Lights: And it is alſo Requiſite, and Neceſſary, that Chriſt ſhould Baptize his Officers with the Holy Ghoſt and with Fire, and this will render them Burning Lights. They are the beſt <hi>Miniſters</hi> that Preach what they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105152:23"/>have Taſted and Experienc'd. Chriſt, in the 7th of St. <hi>Iohn, v.</hi> 38th, ſaith, <hi>He that believes on me, out of his belly ſhall flow Rivers of Living Waters.</hi> This phraſe, out of his Belly, is to be obſerved, he that hath drank of Chriſt's Spiritual VVa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, out of his Belly ſhall flow Rivers of Living VVaters; that which hath ſatisfied and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, ſhall flow out to the Refreſhment of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. O how earneſt, and importunate, ſhould Chriſtians be at the Throne of Grace, that God would furniſh the Church with a skilful and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive <hi>Miniſtry. Aaron</hi> was to have Golden Bells, and Pomegranates on the Hem of his Garment round about, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.33, 24, 35. The Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granates might point at the Sweet Savour of Chriſt's Death and Sacrifice. And this was to be ſounded out by the Apoſtles Preaching, as Golden Bells. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> doth apply theſe Bells to the Apoſtles, and Goſpel <hi>Miniſters,</hi> in his Dialogue with <hi>Tryphis</hi> the <hi>Jew.</hi> Theſe do depend on the Garment of Chriſt, as High Prieſt of the Church. They are, by Preaching, to ſound out the Sufferings, and Death of Chriſt, to the World. <hi>Solomon</hi> made a Molten Sea, that contained a great quantity of Water, and it was put upon Twelve Oxen, three of which looked to each of the Quarters of the World: And this Sea ſeems to point out the Blood of Chriſt, and its abundant Merit; and the Twelve Apoſtles, as ſo many Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Oxen, were to bare, and carry this Sea of Blood into the ſeveral parts of the World, by the Preaching of the Goſpel, that Soules might be waſhed in this Spiritual Sea, the Great Trumpet was to be blown, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. laſt. the Spiritual Jubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105152:23"/>was to be Proclaim'd, and, Who ſhould do this but the Miniſters of the Goſpel? Chriſt was to be lifted up, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.22. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. as a Standard, and to ſtand, as an Enſign, to draw periſhing ſinners together to ſeek Righteouſneſs, and Salvation in him. A Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port was to be made of Jeſus Chriſt, the ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his Knowledge was to be ſhed abroad; And who are fit Spiritual Incenſe-Pans, or Veſſels to bear the Name of Chriſt before the World, but the Miniſters of the New Teſtament. Though theſe are but as little Children in the Eye of the World, becauſe of mean Quality, and Degree, as to their outward State; yet ſuch Little Children ſhall be enabled by the Power of God to Lead Herds of thoſe that have been Lions, Tygers, and Bears, but now become Tame, and Gentle Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.6, 7. They are to Reclaim Men from their Savage, Cruel, Barbarous Nature, and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and to Reduce them to the Meekneſs and Gentleneſs of Chriſt. They are to Hew Sinners out of the Common Quarry they are in, to Fiſh and draw them out of the Dead Sea, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17.10, 11. to cut them out of the Wild Olive, not to be Burnt, but to be Grafted; they are to out the Navel of Sinners, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.4. and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate them from Old <hi>Adam.</hi> They are to beget Men in Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. they are to Ingraft Men into Chriſt, and to Eſpouſe them to Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. They are to encourage the Deject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Diſconſolate. In this ſenſe the Breaſts of the Church are as the Cluſters of the Vine, they contain excellent Wine of Conſolation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.11. Soules may ſuck, and be ſatisfied with the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105152:24"/>Breaſts of her Conſolation, <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.8. They are to ſtrengthen the weak hands, to confirm the Feeble Knees; to ſay to them, that are of a fearful heart, be ſtrong, and fear not, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.3, 4. They are to Feed, Strengthen, and Nouriſh Soules. The Breaſts of the Church are as Towers, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.10. The ſame <hi>Hebrew</hi> Word is uſed to fignifie a <hi>Pulpit,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Migdal.</hi> The Pulpits of Miniſters are the Churches Breaſts, whereby Soules are Fed and Nouriſhed. Not only their Lips, but their Souls muſt Preach. Therefore it is put in the Feminine Gender, <hi>Cokeleth, Eccleſ.</hi> 1.1. So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.11. They that Publiſh it, is alſo put in the Feminine Gender, to intimate, it is Souls that muſt Preach. There is need of a Mighty Power to work in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that they may Pray Fervently, Preach and Exhort Zealouſly, 1 <hi>Col.</hi> laſt. Have large and capacious Soules, that may have room for all the concerns of the Church, and be ſuitably affected with the Burdens. Temptations, Afflictions, Soul-Troubles, and Diſtreſſes of every particular Chriſtian, to Watch over the Members of the Church, to care for them, to Inſtruct, Warn, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, to deny themſelves, to ſpend, and be ſpent for Chriſt: O what a Preſence, Aſſiſtance, and Powerful Influence of the Spirit doth this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; to fit, and enable Miniſters for the full Diſcharge of their Office: O therefore wreſtle with God, cry mightily to him, to Raiſe up ſuch Able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, that may be filled with the Spirit, and Preach in the Demonſtration of the Spirit, and of Power, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4. And be earneſt to reſcue Souls from the Power of Darkneſs, and to Tranſlate them into
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105152:24"/>the Kingdom of God's dear Son. That they may be Pens in the Hand of the Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. to Write the Doctrine of the Goſpel in the Mindes and Hearts of Men, that their Mouthes may be a Sword in the hand of the Spirit, to wound the Old Man to Death, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29. And that the Word they Preach, may be a Hammer in the Hand of the Spirit, to break the Rocky Hearts of Men in Pieces; and, as a Fire to burn up the Droſs of Men, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame their Soules with Love to, and Zeal for God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:105152:25"/>
            <head>BOOKS <hi>Printed for</hi> Thomas Parkhurſt, <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Three-Crowns <hi>in</hi> Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, <hi>near</hi> Mercers-Chapel.</head>
            <p>THE Fountain of Life opened, or a Diſpla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt in his Eſſential and Mediatoral Glory; containing Forty two Sermons on various Texts. Wherein the Impetration of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Jeſus Chriſt is orderly unfolded, as it was begun, carried on, and finiſhed by his Covenant Tranſaction, myſterious Incarnation, ſolemn Call and Dedication, bleſſed Offices, deep Abaſement and Supereminent Advancement.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of the Soul of Man, wherein the Divine Original, excellent and immortal Nature of the Soul are opened; its Love and Inclination to the Body, with the neceſſity of its Separation from it, conſidered and improved. The Exiſtence, Operations and States of ſeparated Souls both in Heaven and Hell immediately after Death, aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, diſcuſſed, and variouſly applied. Divers knotty and difficult Queſtions about departed Souls both Philoſophical and Theological, ſtated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined.</p>
            <p>The Method of Grace in bringing home the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Redemption, contrived by the Father, and accompliſhed by the Son, through the Effectual Application of the Spirit unto God's Elect, being the ſecond Part of Goſpel Redemption.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105152:25"/>
            <p>The Divine Conduct or Myſtery of Providence, its Being and Efficacy aſſerted and vindicated; all the Methods of Providence in our courſe of Life opened, with Directions how to apply and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them.</p>
            <p>Navigation ſpiritualiz'd, or a New Compaſs for Seamen, conſiſting of Thirty Two Points of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Obſervations, profitable Applications, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reflections, all concluded with ſo many ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Poems, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Saint indeed, the great Work of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
            <p>A Touchſtone of Sincerity, or Signs of Grace, and Symptoms of Hypocriſie, being the ſecond Part of the Saint indeed.</p>
            <p>A Token for Mourners, or Boundaries for Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for the Death of Friends.</p>
            <p>Husbandry ſpiritualiz'd; or the Heavenly uſe of Earthly Things. All theſe Nine by Mr. <hi>John Flavell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sermons and Diſcourſes on ſeveral Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; by the late Reverend and Learned <hi>David Clarkſon,</hi> B. D. and ſometime Fellow of <hi>Clare-Hall, Cambridge. Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of Thoughtfulneſs for the Morrow. With an Appendix concerning the immoderate Deſire of foreknowing Things to come.</p>
            <p>Of Charity in reference to other Mens ſins.</p>
            <p>A Sermon directing what we are to do after a ſtrict Enquiry whether or no we truly Love God.</p>
            <p>A calm and ſober Enquiry concerning the Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of a Trinity in the Godhead.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105152:26"/>
            <p>A Sermon preach'd on the late Day of Thank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giving, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 2. 1697. To which is perſix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dr. <hi>Bates</hi>'s Congratulatory Speech to the King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> All theſe Eleven by Mr. <hi>John Howe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Good of Early Obedience, or the Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vantage of bearing the Yoke of Chriſt betime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Almoſt Chriſtian, or the falſe Profeſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tried and Caſt. <hi>Duodecimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Spiritual Wiſdom improved againſt Temptat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on. <hi>Duodecimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Viſion of the Wheels ſeen by the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ezechiel. Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon of Unity, or Two Sticks made one <hi>Quarto.</hi> All Five by <hi>Matth. Mead,</hi> Paſtor of Church of Chriſt at <hi>Stepney.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcourſes upon the Rich Man and <hi>Lazaru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three laſt Sermons of Mr. <hi>Cruſo;</hi> To which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> added a Sermon on <hi>Novemb.</hi> 5. 1697. <hi>Octav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Both by <hi>Tim. Cruſo,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>His Funeral Sermon, preach'd by <hi>Matth. Mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Life and Death of Mr. <hi>Philip Henry,</hi> Mini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Whitchurch,</hi> in <hi>Shorpſhire,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> died <hi>June</hi> 24. 1696 Recommended by Dr. <hi>Bates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David Jones</hi>'s Sermon in <hi>Ember-Week,</hi> preache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Qualifications requiſite, towards the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving a Divine Revelation. A Sermon preac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed in the Cathedral Church of St. <hi>Paul, Janua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the 2d. 1699. Being the Firſt, for this Year, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Lecture, Founded by the Honourable <hi>Robe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Boyle,</hi> Eſq; By <hi>Samuel Bradford,</hi> M. A. Rector <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> St. <hi>Mary le Bow.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105152:26"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
